Guide to the Elmer Ellsworth Brown Papers MC.16
New York University Archives
Elmer Ellsworth Brown Papers
1827-1936
New York University Archives
Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934
MC.16
11.92 Linear Feet in 29 boxes and 2 folders in a shared oversized flat box
Elmer Ellsworth Brown was the Chancellor of New York University from 1911 until his retirement in 1933. Materials in this collection span the years 1827-1936 and include papers from Brown's family members along with documents related to his work as a teacher, principal, United States Commissioner of Education, and Chancellor of NYU. The bulk of this collection is comprised of correspondence with his wife and family, his daily diaries, and mementos from his travels to Europe.
Arrangement
Files are arranged either alphabetically or chronologically within each series.
This collection is divided into eleven series.
Series I: Biographical and genealogical materials, 1880-1934
Series II: Family correspondence and related materials, 1827-1935
Series III: Verse, 1903-1933
Series IV: Address books, diaries, journals, and ledgers, 1875-1934
Series V: Public life, cultural activities, and travel, 1901-1903
Series VI: Personal and professional correspondence, 1869-1911
Series VII: Pre-retirement awards and tributes, 1905-1933
Series VIII: Retirement, 1932-1935
Series IX: Obituaries, funeral arrangements, and memorial service, 1932-1935
Series X: Estate papers, 1932-1936
Series XI: Printed and Published Materials, 1931-1935
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection span the years 1827-1936 and include papers from Brown's family members along with documents related to his work as a teacher, principal, United States Commissioner of Education, and Chancellor of NYU. The bulk of this collection is comprised of correspondence with his wife and family, his daily diaries, and mementos from his travels to Europe.
Biography of Elmer Ellsworth Brown
Elmer Ellsworth Brown (1861-1934), educator and university administrator, was born in Kiantone, Chautaugua County, New York, on August 26, 1861. He was the fourth and youngest child of Russell McCrary and Electa Louisa (Sherman) Brown. His father's ancestors moved from Connecticut to Albany County, New York in the early eighteenth century and settled in western New York around 1800. In 1862, the family moved west to Sublette, Illinois, but returned shortly thereafter to Kiantone when Elmer's father enlisted in the Union Army. In 1864, the family returned to Sublette following Russell Brown's discharge from the Army due to poor health.
The Brown family lived in poverty, relying on income and produce from their farm. Additional income was received through a soldier's pension and money earned by the children performing neighborhood chores. Russell Brown, the grandson of a Congregational minister, completed his formal schooling in New York State, but was unable to attend college due to financial contraints. Despite this, Russell Brown continued to educate himself by reading literature and poetry. He shared this activity with his children. Russell Brown's four children went on to acquire college educations and entered into professional careers.
Elmer Brown did not begin formal schooling until he was eight years old. In 1874, while attending Sublette High School, Brown competed with other students for a teacher certification and finished first in the county examinations. Unfortunately, due to his young age, he was not appointed as a teacher. Two years later, he entered the Illinois State Normal University and began a period of both teaching and study.
In 1878, Brown became principal of the public schools in Rockport, Illinois and in 1880, he served as a teacher in the public schools in Astoria, Illinois. In 1881, he graduated from Illinois State Normal University and became principal of public schools in Belvidere, Illinois, serving there until 1884. His older brother, Isaac Eddy Brown, held the position of State Secretary of the Illinois Y.M.C.A. and Elmer became Assistant Secretary, a position in which he occupied until 1887.
In the fall of 1887, Brown entered the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor to study the theory and practice of education under Professor William H. Payne and the history and philosophy of education under Professor Burke A. Hinsdale. He completed the four-year course in two years, graduating in June 1889 with Phi Beta Kappa honors. Two days following commencement, Brown married his cousin Fanny F. Eddy of Detroit. Fanny was the daughter of the Reverend Zachery Eddy, a prominent Michigan clergyman.
Elmer and Fanny Brown traveled to Europe in 1889 and settled in Germany, where Elmer enrolled in the University of Halle-Wittenberg to study the philosophy of education. At the end of the academic year, he was awarded a Ph.D. degree after completing and publishing his German-language thesis, "The Position of States Toward the Church and Carrying Out Religious Education in the Schools in Prussia, England, and the United States" (1890). Returning to the United States, Brown became a high school principal in Jackson, Michigan, a position he held until 1891 when he was selected as acting Assistant Professor of the Art and Science of Teaching in the University of Michigan. He temporarily replaced his mentor, Dr. Hinsdale. Before his first year was completed, Brown received an invitation to join the faculty at the University of California at Berkeley.
Brown spent the next fourteen years at Berkeley. He was appointed the first chair of the Science and Art of Teaching in 1892 and he soon formulated plans for the organization and development of the University's Department of Pedagogy. During his tenure at the University of California, Brown wrote his best known scholarly works, The Origins of American State Universities (1903) and The Making of Our Middle Schools (1903), a historical study of secondary education in the United States. Through his publications and work in developing the pedagogy department at Berkeley, Brown became a national figure in education. In 1905, he was elected to serve a two-year term as president of the National Council on Education.
In 1906, Elmer Brown was appointed United States Commissioner of Education by President Theodore Roosevelt. Building upon the work of his predecessor, William Torrey Harris, he enlarged the Bureau of Education by establishing special divisions in higher education and school administration. He also extended the services of the Bureau throughout the country. As national spokesman for education, Brown traveled extensively, addressing problems and issues in elementary, secondary, and higher education. A selection of his many speeches and essays were published in Government By Influence and Other Addresses (1910). He was reappointed to the role of United States Commissioner of Education by William Howard Taft in 1908 and served until 1911, when he was chosen to be Chancellor of New York University. He held the office of Chancellor of New York University until his retirement in 1933 and then the title of Chancellor Emeritus until his death in New York City on November 3, 1934.
Sources:
Frusciano, Thomas J. "Elmer Ellsworth Brown: Mohonker, Scholar, and Educator, 1861-1934," unpublished address delivered at the Hudson Valley & Mohonk Heritage Program, Lake Mohonk, New York, July 10, 1984. New York University Archives.
Jones, Theodore Francis, ed. New York University, 1832-1932. New York: New York University Press, 1933.
Voorhis, Harold O. A Tribute to Elmer Ellsworth Brown, 1861-1934. New York: Hall of American Artists, New York University, 1944.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers were transferred to the University Archives from the Office of the Vice President and Secretary in 1976. Materials found in Series XI: Printed and Published Materials, 1931-1935 were donated by Frances Eddy Lodge in 1983.
Genealogies.; Indians, Treatment of -- North America; Arbitration and award, International.; Belvidere (Ill.); Ledgers (account books); Address books; Education -- Philosophy; Education -- Study and teaching -- United States; Curricula.; Oakland (Calif.).; Broadsides.; Letterpress copybooks.; Berkeley (Calif.); Mohonk, Lake (N.Y.); Obituaries.; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906.; Wills; Sublette (Ill.); Manuscripts for publication.; New York (N.Y.).; Account books; Biographies.; Diaries; Programs (documents); Pamphlets.; Lake Mohonk Conference of Friends of the Indian; Keppel, Frederick, 1845-1912; Louisiana Purchase Exposition Co. (Saint Louis, Mo.); Lake Mohonk Conference on International Arbitration (Mohonk Lake, N.Y.); Muensterberg, Hugo; Pan-American Exposition (1901: Buffalo, NY); New York University; Grandi, Dino, 1895-; Gilman, Daniel Colt, 1831-1909; Howison, George Holmes, 1834-1917; Harris, William Torrey, 1835-1909; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1852-1937; James, Edmund J. (Edmund Janes), 1855-1925; Kellogg, Martin; University of the State of New York; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Churchill, Winston, 1871-1947; Cuerly, Ellwood P.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; Draper, A. S. (Andrew Sloan), 1848-1913; Eddy Family Association; Eddy, Zachery; Finley, John; Angell, James Burill, 1829-1916; Armory Show (1913: New York, N.Y.); Bailey, Thomas P.; Brown, Electra Louisa; Brown, Fanny Eddy; Brown, Isaac Eddy; Brown, Russell McCary; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; American Academy of Arts and Letters; Alameda County (CA) Teachers' Institute; MacCracken, Henry Mitchell, 1840-1918; Young Men's Christian Association (Illinois); Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Smiley, Daniel; Slate, Frederick; Scripture, E. W. (Edward Wheeler), 1864-1945; Sanford, Emerson C.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Pardee, George; Wheeler, Benjamin Ide, 1854-1927; Voorhis, Harold O.; University of Michigan; University of Halle-Wittenberg (Germany); University of California, Berkeley. School of Education; United States. Bureau of Education; Thorndike, Edward L. (Edward Lee), 1874-1949
- Series I: Biographical and genealogical materials, 1880-1934
  Scope and Contents note
  The initial files of the Brown personal papers contain biographical and genealogical material on the families of Elmer Ellsworth Brown and Fanny Eddy Brown. Numerous biographical sketches of Elmer Brown, the Brown family tree, a biographical sketch of Isaac Eddy Brown, notes on the Brown family compiled by Elmer Brown, and material relating to the Eddy Family Association are also included in these files.
  - Biographical Sketches, 1906-1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Immediate Relatives of Elmer E. Brown and Fanny E. Brown, 1902, 1927, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Isaac Eddy: Family Tree and Biographical Sketch, undated, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brown Family: Notes compiled by Elmer E. Brown, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cowles, Dwight L. and Mary Brown, [1924] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Eddy, Nathan, and Samuel Cochran: Revolutionary War Record, 1902, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Eddy Family Association, 1921-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marriage Certificate (informal): Elmer E. Brown and Fanny F. Eddy, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1880, circa 1900s-1920s (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Family correspondence and related materials, 1827-1935
  This series contains extensive correspondence exchanged between Elmer Brown and his wife Fanny, 1886-1929, including letters from Elmer Brown when he was in Berkeley during the San Francisco earthquake on April 18, 1906; correspondence and miscellaneous papers of members of the Eddy family and Brown family; collections of verse written by Elmer Brown, Fanny Brown, other relatives and friends; and wills, obituaries, and tributes concerning Fanny Brown.
  - Elmer E. Brown to Fanny Eddy, 1886 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elmer E. Brown to Fanny E. Brown, 1896 July (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - EEB to FEB, 1898 June-July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - EEB to FEB, 1901 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - EEB to FEB, 1904 July, September (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - EEB to FEB: San Francisco Earthquake, Apr. 18, 1906, 1906 April-May (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - EEB to FEB (from Washington DC), 1906 June-September (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - EEB to FEB, 1907 June, September (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - EEB to FEB, 1908 May-June, September (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - EEB to FEB, 1909 June-July (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - EEB to FEB, 1911 March (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - EEB to FEB, 1919 September-October (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - EEB to FEB, 1925 October-December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - EEB to FEB, 1926 January-March (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - EEB to FEB, 1929 May-July (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - EEB to FEB (from Lake Mohonk), 1929 September (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - EEB to FEB (from Coney Island), 1929 October (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - EEB to FEB (enroute to/from Cuba), 1929 November (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - EEB to FEB (enroute to/from Costa Rica and Cuba), 1929 November (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - EEB to FEB (telegram), 1931 November (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - EEB to FEB, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Fanny Eddy to Elmer E. Brown, 1889 June (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fanny E. Brown to EEB, 1904 June (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - FEB to EEB, 1908 August (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - FEB to EEB, 1910 May-September (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - FEB to EEB, 1911 February, 1912 March-November (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - FEB to EEB, 1919 April-October (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - FEB to EEB, 1924 February-April (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - FEB to EEB, 1925 January-February, October-December (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - FEB to EEB, 1926 January-March (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - FEB to EEB, 1927 December (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 June (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 September (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - FEB to EEB, 1929 October-December (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - FEB to EEB, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - FEB to EEB: Verse, 1891-1932 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - FEB to EEB: Verse, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - FEB: Manuscripts of Verse, 1886-1929, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - FEB: Collection of Modern Verse in University Library, 1923-1933 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - FEB: Wills, Obituaries, and Tributes, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Browning, Dorothy (niece), 1927, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cochran, David H. (uncle), 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Curtiss, Alice Eddy (sister) and Edward (brother-in-law), 1934, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Eddy, Frank W. (brother) and Florence (sister-in-law), undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Eddy, Zachary (father): Sermons, Notes, Correspondence, circa 1820s-1890s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Lyons, Albert E. (nephew; son of Edith and Albert Lyons), [1931]-1935 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lyons, Edith (sister) and Albert (brother-in-law), 1890, 1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Lyons, Lucia E. (niece; daughter of Edith and Albert Lyons), 1932-1934, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Lucking, Frances Eddy (niece), undated, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mundy, Kathleen (niece; daughter of Frank W. Eddy), undated, 1932-1935 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Munger, Florence (niece), 1927, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Standish, Mrs. Colburn (niece; daughter of Frank W. Eddy), 1923 ,1930, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Treat, Alice (niece), 1901, 1922-1935 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Treat, Ethel (niece), undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Treat, Leonard A. (brother-in-law): The New England Primer, (1887) 1889 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Treat, Rev. Roger Eddy (nephew), 1932-1935 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Brown, Alice (niece), 1934-1935, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Electa Louisa Sherman (mother), 1889, 1899, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Brown, Isaac Eddy (brother), 1891-1927 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Brown, Russell McCrary (father), 1887, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fairchild, Lillian (sister), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - McMurry, Fred R. (nephew; son of Lida B. McMurry), 1922-1935 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - McMurry, Karl F. (nephew; son of Lida B. McMurry), 1911-1935 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - McMurry, Lida B. (sister), 1889-1933 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - McMurry, Lida B. (sister), 1934 January-October (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - McMurry, Lida B. (sister), 1934-1935 November (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Ponafidine, Madame Emma (distant cousin? and author), 1922-1935 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Folder not found (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Family Correspondence re: Position of Chancellor at New York University: Isaac Eddy Brown, Frank W. Eddy, and Leonard A. Treat, 1911 March-April (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Family Correspondence, Miscellaneous and Unidentified: Corydon Brown, Fred Cowles, Frances Marvin Eddy, Samuel A. Eddy, Florence Knapp, Frank M. McMurry, Janet Munger, Mary[?], Lorraine[?], and Peggy [?], 1900-1934, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Series III: Verse, 1903-1933
  This series contains contains writings of friends and relatives of Elmer Brown in manuscript form.
  - Arnold, J. Loring, 1923-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Lyons, Edith Eddy, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Maclean, Eda, 1928 February, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Walker, F. A, 1927 November, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Authors: James Buckham, Grace Keat Hill, Robert Underwood Johnson, Edwin Markham, Lawrence McLouth, Stephen Phillips, Leon J. Richardson, Jones B. Smith [EEB?], and other anonymous authors, 1921-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Relatives: Alice M. Eddy, Fanny E. Brown, Elmer E. Brown, Edith E. Lyons, Alice E. Treat, Kathleen Mundy, F. C. Hudson, 1903-1907, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Elmer Ellsworth Brown: Annotated volumes (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Scope and Contents
    Two published volumes of poetry Elmer Ellsworth Brown wrote additional poems in. One volume was the first copy from the printer of Brown's 1923 book of poetry "Victory and Other Verse," which he inscribed to his wife and continued to add poems in blank spaces for several years. There is a tipped in photo of brown and pasted to the back cover is the letter of gift from Arthur H. Nason. The other volume is a book of poetry entitled "Verses" by Lawrence A. McLouth. It is inscribed to Brown and his wife, and Brown used some of the back pages to compose a poem entitled "Lullaby."
    Separated Materials
    These two volumes were orginally a part of the Faculty Publications Collection (RG 1.1). Upon a survey of the collection, a determination was made that, due to the handwritten annotations, these books had research value independent of their being faculty publications and were added to the Elmer Ellsworth Brown Papers.
- Series IV: Address books, diaries, journals, and ledgers, 1875-1934 (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15)
  Elmer Brown maintained a diary for each year from 1875-1934, with many years containing incomplete entries. Along with this valuable personal record are numerous account books, journals, ledgers, all of which document his financial affairs, and address books of people he associated or corresponded with throughout his professional life.
- Series V: Public life, cultural activities, and travel, 1901-1903
  This series includes subject files, arranged alphabetically, pertaining to personal and professional activities pursued by Brown outside the area of education. These files include material on his travel to Europe in 1923; the Lake Mohonk conferences on Indian and Other Dependent People, and International Arbitration; invitations and programs to numerous social and cultural activities in New York City; and a large collection of musical, opera, and theater programs.
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1914, 1916 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - American Institute, 1914 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Armory Show, 1913 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Ethnic Groups, Meetings re:, circa 1910s-1930s (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1923 July-August (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Europe, Trip to, 1923 September-November (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Europe, Trip to, 1932 March (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Events in which EEB participated, 1911-1930 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Grandi, Dino (Italian Minister of Foreign Affairs): Welcome Ceremony, Nov. 21, 1931), 1931 October-November (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Health and Medicine, including International Congresses, circa 1910s-1930s (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Institute of Politics, 1921-1933 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Invitations (formal) and Acknowledgments from Distinguished People, 1912-1929, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Programs, 1911-1931, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Mohonk, Lake: Conference on Indian..., 1917 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Mohonk, Lake, Conference on International Arbitration, 1912-1917 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Mohonk, Lake, Mountain House (Mr and Mrs. Daniel Smiley, Proprietors), 1911-1932 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Musical Events, Programs of, 1911-1923, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - New York City Official Occassions, 1912-1922, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - New York Commercial Centenery Commission, 1914 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Pan American Exposition, Buffalo, New York 1901: Printed Material (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Peace Congresses and Related Affairs, 1912-1928, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Religious Services and Lectures: Programs and Notices, 1912-1929, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Theater Programs, 1912-1920 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Theater Programs, 1921-1923, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Personal and professional correspondence, 1869-1911
  Brown's student and professional activities in education are documented extensively in these files of correspondence and related papers. This includes his initial schooling in Sublette, Illinois, his years at the Illinois State Normal University, service as principal of public schools in Belvidere, Illinois, his tenure as Assistant State Secretary of the Illinois Y.M.C.A., his student years at the University of Michigan, 1887-1889, and at the University of Halle-Wittenberg in Germany, 1889-1890, high school principal in Jackson, Michigan, 1890-1891, and acting Assistant professor of the Science and Art of Teaching, 1891-1892.
  A large number of correspondence files concern the development of the Department of Pedagogy at the University of California at Berkeley, 1892-1906. These files include extensive correspondence with Brown's colleagues at Berkeley such as presidents Martin Kellogg and Benjamin I. Wheeler, and professors Frederick Slate, George Howison, and numerous educators across the United States, including James B. Angell, Nicholas Murray Butler, William Torrey Harris, Thomas P. Bailey, Jr., E. C. Sanford, Edmund J. James, Andrew S. Draper, Ellwood P. Cubberly, Hugo Muensterberg, John H. Finley, Winston Churchill, Henry M. MacCracken, Daniel Colt Gilman, E. W. Scripture, and Governor George Pardee of California. Of particular interest are letters from John Dewey when the educator was serving as a professor of philosophy at the University of Michigan and the University of Chicago. Also included in the professional correspondence files are departmental reports on student enrollment, Brown's course notebooks for "Theory of Education" and "School Systems," and printed material relating to both the Department of Pedagogy and general university concerns. Material concerning Brown's activities as U.S. Commissioner of Education, 1906-1911, include correspondence files and letter books of outgoing correspondence. The final folder relates to Brown's decision to accept the invitation to become Chancellor of New York University in 1911.
  - Correspondence and Papers, 1869-1881, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Illinois State Normal University: Miscellaneous Notes; Fine Arts and Literature Notes, 1878-1888 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Belvidere, Illinois (Principal of Public Schools), 1881-1884 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Belvidere, Illinois: School Reports, 1881-1884 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Illinois State Y.M.C.A. (Assistant State Secretary), 1885-1887 (Box 19, Folder 5)